Guide to the Hopkins Transportation Collection M0175
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hopkins Transportation Collection
1711-1959
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Southern Pacific Transportation Company
M0175
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes, 2 map-folders)
Miscellaneous items once belonging to the Hopkins Transportation Library at Stanford.
Scope and Content
Material concerning railroads, shipping, automobiles, and transportation which was once part of the Hopkins Transportation Library at Stanford. This is one of several collections named the Hopkins Transportation Collection: see also M0097 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082956); M0164 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082992); M0200 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082990) and others. This collection contains multiple accessions from various donors over many years, including a ledger from an English sailing vessel dated 1711-1757, railroad stock and bond certificates signed by Hopkins Huntington, deeds and legal documents involving a variety of rail companies (including a list of founding stockholders for the Oakland Railroad Co. in 1868), and a great deal of Southern Pacific Railroad material, some of which was sent directly to the Hopkins Library while it was under the care of director Jeanette Hitchcock in the 1940s. Stanford also holds Southern Pacific’s archive (M1010). Nearly all Hopkins Transportation photographs have been filed in M0234 (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4082994).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Hopkins Transportation Library at Stanford when it closed. Various sources originally.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Transportation -- History.; Hopkins Transportation Library.; Railroads -- History; Shipping -- History; Automobiles -- History; Southern Pacific Transportation Company
- Series 1. Railroad
  - Southern Pacific Railroad
    - memo re: Drumm Street Station, San Francisco, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      "Found in wall of Merchant's Exchange Building during renovation, January-February 1974; SP had rented a floor in the building"
    - program/menus, 1916-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Seventh Annual Reunion & Luncheon of Southern Pacific Pensioners, Palace Hotel May 10, 1916; 51st Anniversary, Driving the Last Spike at Promontory, Utah, Luncheon of Retired Employees of Southern Pacific Company May 10, 1920; Southern Pacific Special Train, Los Angeles to San Francisco, His Excellency Nikita S. Krushchev September 20, 1959
    - cards, notices, ephemera, circa 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Shasta Daylight press releases, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Many of the press releases are torn and damaged
    - magazine and newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - timetables, 1888-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Southern Pacific-Central Pacific unmerging (pamphlets, proceedings and statements), 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - documents and pamphlets by or about SPRR, 1878-1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Letter From the Secretary of War Concerning the Location of Southern Pacific and Texas Pacific Railroads Through Fort Yuma Reservation and Across the Colorado River, January 18, 1878; Richard S. Spofford, Argument Before the Committee on Railroads of the US Senate, March 12, 1878; Letter From the Secretary of the Interior, Communicating In Answer to a Senate Resolution … in Relation to the Construction of a Railroad through the Public Domain in the Territory of Arizona January 16, 1879; Completion of a Southern Pacific Railroad and Telegraph Line, June 3, 1880; Pacific Coast Law Journal Supplement, The Railroad Tax Case, County of San Mateo Vs. SPRR, September 25th, 1882; George Draper Stratton obituary reprint, 1905; “The System” and the Southern Pacific Incidentally E.A. Hayes and the Sorrows of the Prune Rancher [circa 1906]; Rules and Specification governing the Uniforming of Employees, 1910; United States vs. SPRR Opinion of Judge Bledsoe, August 28, 1919; Adequate Transportation Must Not Result in Wasteful Duplication of Facilities Under the National Transportation Act of 1920, April 2, 1929; Re-Issue of Special Notices and Circulars, 1939
    - advertising brochures, maps, etc., 1883-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      SPRR-published booklets and brochures related to tourism and travel, especially in California and the West. Some include route maps, timetables, photographs and illustrations.
    - Coast Line Route, California (Denison News Co., photogravures by Albertype Co.), circa 1890s (Box 5, Folder 1)
      23 leaves of mounted plates, 27 x 32 cm.
    - Foote, Cone & Belding advertisement proofs, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - posters (Map-folder 7)
      Statement re: war 1943; Calendar 1949; Shasta Daylight advertisement [c.1949]
  - Other Railroads
    - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad briefs & report, ca.1872-1873, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      legal publications re: State of Maryland suit 1872-1873; Report on Employee Library 1887
    - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Relief Dept. Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1894-1897 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad stockholders letters, 1933, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Central New York & Western Railroad stock coupons, circa 1897-1904 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Central Pacific Railroad (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Includes C.H. Redington's Employee Season Ticket 1874; Huntington, Hopkins & Co. shipping receipt 1875; draft correspondence 1889; undated notes
    - Central Pacific Railroad bond, 1863, stamped paid 1893 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Central Pacific/Huntington article - Weekly Chronicle, December 27, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - tariffs: California Pacific Railroad 1873; Central Pacific Railroad 1875 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hawaii Consolidated Railroad, Ltd. deed, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - London & North Eastern Railway travel poster: Cambridge on the London & North Eastern Railway of England & Scotland (Baynard Press) (Map-folder 8)
    - Los Angeles-Pacific Railroad Balloon Route ad, Los Angeles Times, May 11, 1901 (Map-folder 7)
      Color, full page advertisement
    - Mexican International Railroad Co. deed, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Oakland Railroad Company stock subscription list, 1868 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Ocean Shore Railroad documents re: grading & right-of-way 1905-1907; capital asset distribution 1926 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Ocean Shore Railroad research notes and clippings (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Pittsburgh Shawmut & Northern Railroad Company reorganization memo, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - misc. rail ephemera, 1842-1956 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 19th. c newspaper clipping re: sleeping car, circa 1860s-1870s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - First Transcontinental Railroad - 75th Anniversary of Completion, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - railroad history organizations, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Mostly fliers for events.
    - Christmas Greetings [holiday cards from transportation companies; most sent to Hopkins Library], 1940s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - cable railways [photostats of articles, etc.] (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - card file: manuscript bibliography of reports related to railroads, circa 1880s (Box 4)
      Index of articles and reports written on the back of unused SPRR freight forms, possibly by Hopkins himself. Paper is very brittle and in some cases damaged.
    - handbill: Reduced Railroad Fares! Farmers! Colonists! And All Seeking Homes in the Great West, Can Purchase Colonist's Tickets From Ithaca...For Sale Only at the Ticket Office of F.W. Phillips (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Railroad bonds & stock certificates, 1862-1902 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Oakland, Brooklyn & Fruit Vale Railroad (Charles G. Lathrop) 1902; Oakland Railroad Company (H.E. Huntington) 1893; Portland & Willamette Valley Railway Co. (Timothy Hopkins) 1887; Pacific Cable Railway Co. (Charles G. Lathrop) 1989; San Joaquin Valley Railroad Co. (Pacific Improvement Co.) 1893; Bonds of the County of Santa Clara - San Francisco & San Jose Rail Road Co. 1862, Western Pacific Railroad Co. 1865
    - scrapbooks of newspaper clippings related to railroads, 1954-1956 (Box 6, Items 1-2)
      Two volumes, one covering 1954-55 and the other 1956. Clippings are from San Francisco Examiner, Wall Street Journal, San Francisco News, etc. Many are loose.
  - lantern slide of elevated railroad, possibly New York (Box 9, Folder 1)
    handwritten label is hard to read- may say "L-Road from Bandstand"?
  - misc. copy prints (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Museum ephemera (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Ships & shipping
  - ship ledger, 1711-1757 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Ledger connected with shipping trade in the New World, recording particularly profits of ship Mermaid and sailings to Virginia and the Indies. Detailed trading with names: Benj'm. Robinson, William Woodford, Thos. Montague, Rev'd. Owen Jones, Hy Robinson, Reuben Walsh, Chas. Gryme, Thos. Griffin of Rappahannock River, Va. and of trade with people in St. Christopher, Barbados, Bilboa, Bayonne, Bengal. There are also detailed accounts of ship refitting, purchases of tobacco, rum, sugar and books from Va. Timothy [Ganer?] was master of the Mermaid which sailed from Liverpool and Whitehaven.
  - Signals for the Use of the United States Navy, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Cloth-bound book entitled Signals for the Use of the United States Navy, as adopted by order of the Navy Dept. printed in Washington City in 1813. Included are handwritten and illustrated notes on flags, signals, etc.
  - National Federation of American Shipping Research Reports, July 9, 1947-November 8, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    22 reports on the U.S. Flag Merchant Marine.
  - Maritime Firsts of San Francisco Bay, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Compiled by San Francisco Public Library Reference Department. Pamphlet published in conjunction with "Pacific Festival," September 9-18, 1960.
  - ships, misc. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes political handbill for "steamer Democracy" 1889; program for California Maritime Academy Graduation Excerises on Training Ship Golden Gate, 1943; Time & Tide Supplement to Glasgow Post-Office and Railway Tables 1894; newspaper clippings, etc.
  - Oakland Water Front Company stock certificate [partial], 1868 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series 3. Automotive
  - trucks, misc. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Historical Facts about Early International Harvester Automotive Vehicles; Workhorses of Yesteryear 1982 calendar
  - California DMV Non-Resident Permit, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - sketches of three-wheeled cars (2), 1944 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - copies of articles on trucking, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Gift of Guy Warren to Western Highway Historical Collection
  - scrapbooks of magazine clippings (Box 6, Items 3-6)
    Three volumes. The first is signed "Frank S. Spring 3/13/22" Volume two and three have indices. All 1920s-40s articles from Autocar, Automotive Industries, The Motor, etc. Two drawings were removed from the back of Volume II and are in Box 3 folder 23.
  - oversize photos and drawings (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Transferred from Western Highways Historical Collection due to size (also probably not originally part of WH)
- Series 4. Miscellaneous
  - Reconveyance, Union Trust Co. - Union Traction Co. 1914; Pacific Streamship Co. - County of Santa Cruz deed 1904 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Documents are very dirty from probable flood damage
  - postcards, clippings, etc. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - poster: USS Los Angeles, The Navy's Mighty Sky Ship (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Midwestern Old Settlers and Threshers ephemera (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - alphabetical file with lithograph of horse & carriage (Box 9, Folder 5)